In this three-part video series,
I'll be doing a deep dive into iron.
We'll look at the ferritin blood test,
what that tells us about iron stores,
and why vegetarians
tend to hit the sweet spot
since higher levels are
associated with chronic disease
like type 2 diabetes and cancer.
That's why you can
decrease cancer rates
when you bleed people
through blood donations.
What's the healthiest way to
maintain optimal iron levels?
Let's dig in.
"Are the Lower Iron Stores in
Vegetarians a Risk or a Benefit?"
The ferritin blood test
measures iron stores,
and a typical normal value
is in the 30 to 300 range.
Almost universally,
vegetarians have
lower ferritin levels
than nonvegetarians;
for example, 39 versus 77.
In one of the largest studies
ever done,
using that 30 cut-off
as a sign of iron deficiency,
about half
of the menstruating vegetarians
scored as iron deficient,
compared to only about a third
of the menstruating omnivores.
But lower iron stores
may actually be better,
shooting for scores
between 15,
which is the World Health
Organization's cut-off
for iron deficiency,
and 50,
because levels above 50
are associated with disease.
In that case,
it could be vegetarians
are in the sweet spot,
because iron
is a double-edged sword,
producing free radicals
in the body
that can cause
oxidative damage
to our proteins
and very DNA.
For example,
high iron intake
is a risk factor
for type 2 diabetes,
contributing to all
the cardinal features
of the disease,
and that's true across
the normal range of iron levels,
not just for people with some
kind of iron overload disease.
So, the "elevated" ferritin,
that's a risk factor
for diabetes,
can just be the average
typical ferritin level,
increasing the odds of diabetes
by 20% compared to low levels,
whereas high ferritin
is even worse,
increasing the odds by 43%.
Wait a second, though.
Might higher iron stores
just be a proxy
for more meat consumption?
After all,
based on studies
encompassing
nearly 2 million people,
higher consumption
of all types of meat—
red meat, poultry,
processed, unprocessed—
is associated with
higher rates of diabetes.
Why do we think it's the iron
and not just the saturated fat
and all the other harmful stuff
in meat?
Because genetic evidence
supports a causal link
between increased
systemic iron status
and increased diabetes risk.
In other words,
regardless of what you eat,
if you just happened
to be born with genes
that tend to give you
higher iron stores,
you tend to have
more diabetes risk.
Ideally, we'd prove it
with an interventional trial.
Check it out.
Researchers looked
at lean, healthy men and women
and found out
that the vegetarians
were more insulin sensitive
than the meat eaters.
Prediabetes and type 2 diabetes
are diseases
of impaired insulin sensitivity.
So, the vegetarians
were doing better.
The vegetarians also had
lower ferritin levels.
To test whether
their iron status
might explain
their advantage,
iron levels
in six male meat eaters
were lowered by phlebotomy—
bloodletting,
like donating blood—
to levels similar
to those seen in vegetarians.
So, they were bled
so their ferritin dropped
from over 70
down closer to 30.
And what happened?
Their insulin sensitivity
improved by about 40%.
The iron-lowering trial
using blood draws
demonstrated that iron
is indeed a key factor
in the difference
in insulin resistance
among vegetarians
and meat eaters.
Iron can also be
a double-edged sword
when it comes to cancer.
Cancer can be viewed
as a ferrotoxic disease,
a disease of iron toxicity,
as iron plays
an important role
in oxidative tissue damage
and subsequent
cancer development.
But again, a link between
high iron stores and cancer
could just be a link
between meat consumption
and cancer.
Too bad we couldn't do some
kind of blood donation study
with cancer; oh, but we can.
Decreased cancer risk
after iron reduction.
More than a thousand
cancer-free individuals
randomized to give
blood donations or not
were followed for the next
four and a half years,
and those who gave blood
had a 60% lower risk
of dying from cancer.
Wait! They cut their risk
of dying from cancer
by more than half
just because they donated blood?
The accompanying editorial
remarked that those results
seemed almost too good
to be true!
Reducing one's iron stores
appeared to rapidly decrease
cancer development,
suggesting that just regular
ambient levels of iron stores
may be noxious and constitute
a public health threat.
So, there may be a need
to redefine the normal range
for blood ferritin.
It should be normal
based on what's healthy,
not just based on
what happens to be common.
Yes, when ferritin slips
to less than like 12 ng/mL,
that is too low,
but iron toxicity diseases
may start with ferritin levels
greater than about 50 ng/mL.
So, yes, vegetarians are more
likely to have lower iron stores
compared to non-vegetarians.
However, since high iron stores
are also a risk factor
for certain chronic diseases,
such as type 2 diabetes,
it's recommended
that we all need to make sure
we're not getting too much,
and we can do that
by improving our diet
by consuming more plants
and less meat.